在前一讲中，我们研究了从一个坐标系转换空间速度
In the previous lecture, we looked at transforming spatial velocity from one coordinate frame
到另一个。我们为二维案例做了这个，我们了解了这种关系
to another. We did this for the two-dimensional case and we learned that the relationship
在速度之间由雅可比矩阵给出，该矩阵实际上是一个函数
between velocities is given by a Jacobian matrix which is actually a function of the
两个坐标系之间的相对方向。
relative orientation between the two coordinate frames.
对于三个维度，事情实际上非常相似。所以，这是一个三维的
For three dimensions, things are actually quite similar. So, here is a three-dimensional
参考坐标框架，相对于框架具有空间速度的点
reference coordinate frame, a point which has a spatial velocity with respect to Frame
答：这里是框架B，我们可以描述框架A和框架之间的相对姿势
A. And, here is Frame B and we can describe the relative pose between Frame A and Frame
B.我们可以用红色显示相对于框架B的空间速度和关系
B. We can show in red the spatial velocity with respect to Frame B and the relationship
两者之间由雅可比矩阵给出。对于三维情形，雅可比
between the two is given by a Jacobian matrix. For the three-dimensional case, the Jacobian
矩阵是6x6.而且，它再一次只是相对方向的函数
matrix is 6 x 6. And, once again, it is a function only of the relative orientation
在两个坐标框架之间。它是来自B帧的旋转矩阵的函数
between the two coordinate frames. It’s a function of rotation matrix from Frame B
框架A.以下是工业机器人的示例。
to Frame A. Here is an example of an industrial robot.
并且，如果我应用一组特定的机器人关节角速度，我会得到一个特定的
And, if I apply a particular set of robot joint angle velocities, I obtain a particular
机器人末端执行器的空间速度与这两个量相关
spatial velocity for the robot end effector and those two quantities are related by the
操纵者，雅各比。现在，这假定机器人末端效应器
manipulator, Jacobian. Now, this assumes that the robot end effector
速度是相对于世界坐标系定义的，在此表示为零。它的
velocity is defined with respect to the world coordinate frame, denoted zero here. It’s
通常非常有用地描述末端执行器相对于末端的速度
often very useful to describe the velocity of the end effector with respect to the end
效应器的坐标系。我在这里表示为第6帧。
effector’s coordinate frame. I have denoted here as Frame 6.
现在，我们可以用不同的雅可比矩阵来写这个。这个雅可比矩阵是关联的
Now, we can write this in terms of a different Jacobian matrix. This Jacobian matrix relates
机器人关节角速度以机器人末端执行器速度表示
the robot joint angle velocity to the robot end effector velocity expressed in terms of
第6帧。我们可以为末端效应器写一个表达式
Frame 6. We can write an expression for the end effector’s
根据两个雅可比矩阵，相对于第6帧的空间速度。这雅各比
spatial velocity with respect to Frame 6 in terms of two Jacobian matrices. This Jacobian
是我们之前谈到的标准机器人操纵器雅可比矩阵。
is the standard robot manipulator Jacobian matrix that we have talked about previously.
并且，这个雅可比矩阵负责将速度从帧0转换为帧
And, this Jacobian matrix is responsible for transforming velocity from Frame 0 to Frame
它是从第6帧到第0帧的相对姿势的函数。并且，雅可比
6 and it is a function of the relative pose from Frame 6 to Frame 0. And, that Jacobian
正如我们在上一张幻灯片中介绍的那样，矩阵只是旋转部分的一个功能
matrix, as we introduced in the previous slide, is a function simply of the rotational part
相对姿势。
of the relative pose.